<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: non-technical | Larry Price]]></title>
  <link href="http://larry-price.com/blog/categories/non-technical/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://larry-price.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-08-12T16:57:15-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://larry-price.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Larry Price]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Ollert - Reveal The Data Behind Your Trello Boards]]></title>
    <link href="http://larry-price.com/blog/2014/07/13/ollert-reveal-the-data-behind-your-trello-boards/"/>
    <updated>2014-07-13T17:15:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://larry-price.com/blog/2014/07/13/ollert-reveal-the-data-behind-your-trello-boards</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Introducing <a href="https://ollertapp.com">Ollert</a>, a tool to show you what your <a href="//trello.com">Trello</a> boards can&rsquo;t tell you on their own.</p>

<p>Trello does a great job of telling you about the here and now of your Trello boards; who&rsquo;s working on what task and what is the current state of a task. But what if I want to know about the state of the whole project? How many work items have we finished in the past sprint, iteration, or duration of the project? He who does not understand the past is destined to repeat his mistakes ad nauseum.</p>

<p>Ollert is a tool with these ideas in mind. Authorize Ollert access to your Trello account, select the board you would like to learn more about, and see all the battle scars your board has experienced throughout the duration of the project.</p>

<p>Learn about your velocity through a Cumulative Flow Diagram. View your work in progress with a WIP chart. See which labels your team uses most frequently with our label chart. See information about your cards and lists from a historical perspective.</p>

<p><a href="https://ollertapp.com/signup">Create an account</a> with Ollert to show your support. Users who sign up for an Ollert account will have their Trello authorization saved, saving the hassle of authorizing with Trello every time the user visits the site. An Ollert account is perfect for any user who views board progress frequently, or for creating a continuous display on an office monitor.</p>

<p>Since Ollert&rsquo;s initial release <a href="/blog/2014/03/17/sep-startup-weekend-ollert/">several months ago</a>, Ollert now boasts over 4000% faster load times, increased data security using SSL and encrypted cookies, and a more consistent Trello connection experience in all modern web browsers.</p>

<p>Discover Ollert now at <a href="https://ollertapp.com">ollertapp.com</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Lessons Learned during the Conception of Ollert]]></title>
    <link href="http://larry-price.com/blog/2014/06/12/lessons-learned-during-the-conception-of-ollert/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-12T20:32:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://larry-price.com/blog/2014/06/12/lessons-learned-during-the-conception-of-ollert</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>During <a href="http://sep.com">SEP&rsquo;s</a> previous <a href="http://sep.com/labs/">startup weekend</a>, I pitched an idea for a <a href="http://trello.com">Trello</a> Analysis Tool called <a href="https://ollertapp.com">Ollert</a>. In less than three days, a team of 6 built a minimal viable product (MVP) and put it live on the internet. In a little over three months, I have slowly guided Ollert through the legal department, obtained a real domain with security, and fixed a few bugs along the way. I&rsquo;ve learned a thing or two about seeing a hackathon project to fruition that I&rsquo;d like to get in writing.</p>

<h3>1. You Can Never Be Too Prepared</h3>

<p>Before Startup Weekend, I spent days refining my idea and coming up with a cute little proof of concept. I even laid out work items for my developers to work on. When I finally discovered a clever name, I thought my preparation was over.</p>

<p>I was wrong.</p>

<p>Although I requested 5 developers to help me build Ollert, my plans only allowed for two developers to work simultaneously. I didn&rsquo;t realize how hard it would be to keep everyone busy all the time, especially my less-experienced engineers.</p>

<p>Although I did proof-of-concept my idea before we started, I failed to proof-of-concept the more dynamic capabilities a multi-user web application needs to provide. This mistake cost another developer and I the first night of the weekend, plus a bit of the next morning.</p>

<p>Don&rsquo;t even get me started about environment setup. Although I run <a href="http://www.ubuntu.com">Ubuntu</a> natively and had all my developer tools ready before we started work Friday night, the rest of my team were users of That Other Operating System. I should have created a virtual machine with everything all set up, burned it to several USB drives, and let my developers set up VirtualBox without my intervention.</p>

<h3>2. Talk to Legal</h3>

<p>Why do I care about legal? Isn&rsquo;t this my responsibility anyway?</p>

<p>As it turns out, putting a startup weekend project live on the internet before the weekend is over is really cool from a team perspective, but terrifying from a legal perspective. With our MVP, I wasn&rsquo;t using SSL to encrypt user data. I didn&rsquo;t consider how Fog Creek would react once they realized our name is their name backwards. I even had the chutzpah to stick my company&rsquo;s logo in my site&rsquo;s footer.</p>

<p>A quick discussion with management will prepare both sides for the &ldquo;grand reveal&rdquo; if the project makes it to launch. Personally, I&rsquo;d like to see some level of legal counsel in the Startup Weekend &ldquo;pre-pitch&rdquo; session to get feedback before implementation.</p>

<h3>3. Listen</h3>

<p>The second day, one of my developers mentioned using endpoints in the application, and I rejected this idea on the basis that it was too complicated. On the dawn of the final day, we realized that we needed to use his approach or the application would be unusable. This required us to do a lot of rework that could have been avoided. I often think about what other ideas might have been suggested by my team that I may have accidentally ignored.</p>

<h3>4. Easy Tasks</h3>

<p>My assumption going into Startup Weekend was that my team would all be familiar enough with the technology to be able to &ldquo;jump right in&rdquo; or follow along with someone who could. This was a bad assumption.</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s easy to find tasks that <em>I</em> can do. It&rsquo;s much more difficult to find tasks that <em>anyone</em> could do. What are the less-involved tasks on your current project that a less-experienced developer could work on until they&rsquo;re ready to tackle something bigger? Can they set up the database, or the tests? Can you find a guide for them to follow to do these things? If not, you&rsquo;ll have people on your team who don&rsquo;t feel involved but desperately want to help.</p>

<h3>5. Start Small</h3>

<p>Ollert is a pretty big idea, especially for a three-day project. I had high hopes of making it even bigger until the dawn of the final day. I wanted to include some sort of payment system to prove that we would be able to charge people when they sign up without actually charging them. This &ldquo;feature&rdquo; of fake payment has no place in a real product, and would have been misleading at best. We had dozens of ideas for statistics and charts to make it into the website that just weren&rsquo;t that useful.</p>

<p>Limiting scope might have allowed us to come up with a more polished MVP; I walked away the final evening wishing I had left out sign up/in in favor of giving the application more sex appeal.</p>

<h3>Conclusion</h3>

<p>Starting a project is hard. It&rsquo;s even more difficult when you have to delegate most of the work to other people. Startup Weekend is a manger and a mortuary, seeing the birth of many ideas and the death of most. I hope to take this experience and make an even better new product next Startup Weekend.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Takeaways From AgileIndy 2014]]></title>
    <link href="http://larry-price.com/blog/2014/05/14/takeaways-from-agileindy-2014/"/>
    <updated>2014-05-14T20:59:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://larry-price.com/blog/2014/05/14/takeaways-from-agileindy-2014</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="//agileindy.org/conference/">The AgileIndy Conference 2014</a> has come and gone. I wasn&rsquo;t sure what to expect, since it was my first conference, but I came out of it feeling rather positive.</p>

<p>A short list of my favorite things from this year&rsquo;s AgileIndy:</p>

<ul>
<li>Interesting speakers</li>
<li>Good food</li>
<li>Uncomfortable chairs</li>
<li><a href="//twitter.com/search?q=%23agileindy14&amp;src=hash">#agileindy14</a></li>
<li>Free booze</li>
<li>Lots of coffee</li>
<li>Champion dogs</li>
</ul>


<p>Good times. Personally, I found the first half of the day to be superior to the afternoon. I&rsquo;m not sure if it was the speakers or if I&rsquo;m just a morning person, but I&rsquo;m much more interested in discussing what the morning speakers had to say.</p>

<h3>The Dude</h3>

<blockquote><p>We&rsquo;ve got hard problems to solve, we don&rsquo;t need aphorisms, we don&rsquo;t need truisms.
&ndash; David Hussman</p></blockquote>

<p>The event started out with the self-proclaimed &ldquo;Dude,&rdquo; <a href="//devjam.com/">David Hussman of DevJam</a>. I&rsquo;ve previously had some training involving Mr Hussman at <a href="//sep.com">SEP</a>, during which we had trouble explaining our relationship with Agile: gargantuan project, lots of devs, massive codebase, hour-long builds, and an immature implementation of the so-called Scalable Agile Framework. I thought I knew what to expect during this talk, but I was delightfully mistaken. Everything Hussman said during his keynote fit with the conversations I&rsquo;ve been having with my current teammates.</p>

<p>Hussman talked about &ldquo;process mass,&rdquo; or the weight that you carry as you gain more and more process on a project. &ldquo;Measure your success by evidence, not by adherence&rdquo; to the process. What good is completing a story if you don&rsquo;t have anything to show for it, or if you don&rsquo;t have the quality to back it up? Hussman discussed scrum, and the ridiculous concept of &ldquo;scrum of scrums,&rdquo; and potentially even a &ldquo;scrum of scrum of scrums.&rdquo; In his own words, &ldquo;At some point you have to have something other than a naming convention.&rdquo; Getting stuff done and feeling satisfied with your work is much more important than being able to audit the lifetime of a story, or what day of the week your team gets the most done, or how many meetings your ScrumMaster goes to.</p>

<p>Speaking of ScrumMasters (and Product Owners and Tech Leads for that matter), the Dude wants us to think critically about these roles. Why are Scrum Masters and Tech Leads in meetings all day? A Tech Lead mosies into standup in the morning just to say, &ldquo;Yesterday I was in meetings all day, today I&rsquo;m in meetings all day, no blockers.&rdquo; &ldquo;Somehow [we&rsquo;ve] bonded the process to the people,&rdquo; using process to hold team members hostage. We&rsquo;ve found ourselves turning Agile into a bloated mess, and we&rsquo;re in need of people to relieve the pressure.</p>

<h3>Estimation</h3>

<p>During the first break-out session, <a href="//vance.com/">Steve Vance</a> talked about estimation, one of my favorite topics to complain about.</p>

<p>We started out by defining terms. Unfortunately, we use the word &ldquo;estimation&rdquo; to mean almost anything, from the very precise to the very vague. We &ldquo;estimate&rdquo; in T-shirt sizes, story points, days, and hours. We all mean something different when we make an estimation; it all boils down to an opinion. &ldquo;The work is going to take what it takes,&rdquo; and everyone has an opinion on how long that is.</p>

<p>I mentioned hours in the above paragraph as a unit of estimation. This is a particular pet peeve of mine: I absolutely despise estimating in hours. What do we even mean when we estimate in hours? Vance says, &ldquo;When I say hours as in this is going to take 3 hours, that does not mean 3 clock hours.&rdquo; So what <em>does</em> an hour mean? My current team uses a tool called TFS, which actually forces you to answer this question. So we &ldquo;estimate&rdquo; that Danny Developer will be able to accomplish 5 hours of work every day. We just turned Danny&rsquo;s day into hours on a clock. Now we &ldquo;estimate&rdquo; that a task will take &ldquo;about a day,&rdquo; which translates into 8 hours. Note that <code>1 task day != 1 Danny Day</code>. We&rsquo;re estimating tasks in these very precise units (real-life hours), and poor Danny will probably just work a 10-hour day to finish the task in &ldquo;1 day,&rdquo; which is what the team estimated the task would take.</p>

<p>T-shirt sizing or story points should be able to alleviate these problems, but we have to be vigilant not to concretely define these terms. Estimates should always be relative to yesterday&rsquo;s weather and not based on real time frames. Once you&rsquo;ve defined a 5-point story as taking exactly 5 days, you&rsquo;ve destroyed the whole system and you might as well start estimating in hours again.</p>

<h3>Anti-fragility</h3>

<p><a href="//salhir.wordpress.com">Si Alhir</a> discussed the principles of &ldquo;anti-fragility&rdquo; during the pre-lunch session. Anti-fragility is a post-Agile concept. That&rsquo;s right: <em>post-Agile</em>. I know you were just getting used to Agile, but it seems that we&rsquo;ve created a monster that&rsquo;s getting harder and harder to control. Teams find themselves saying &ldquo;They&rsquo;re not Agile, we&rsquo;re Agile&rdquo; when describing the pitfalls of other teams.</p>

<p>So what is anti-fragility? It&rsquo;s easier to define in relative terms. Traditional teams are hurt by change and actively resist change; Agile teams embrace change and are able to inspect and adapt to it; Anti-Fragile teams embrace disorder and are able to adapt and evolve to chaos. &ldquo;Fragile teams want tranquility,&rdquo; while anti-fragile teams &ldquo;gain from stress.&rdquo; Anti-fragility involves shifting from focusing on avoiding risk to focusing on overcoming risk.</p>

<p>&ldquo;What have you removed?&rdquo; Si asks, reiterating Hussman from earlier in the day. &ldquo;More rules, more process causes more fragility.&rdquo; As our Agile teams add process, this becomes more evident. &ldquo;Dependency,&rdquo; &ldquo;the line between dev and test&rdquo;, and &ldquo;centralized power&rdquo; all cause fragility. Sprint cycles every 1-2 weeks cause a constant stress, which &ldquo;will kill you, numb you.&rdquo; Anti-fragile teams prefer &ldquo;acute stress with recovery time&rdquo; caused by overcoming risk as it materializes. The so-called ScrumMaster of an Agile team is protecting the team from risk, contributing to the overall fragility of the team.</p>

<p>&ldquo;The most fragile thing in the Agile world is teams,&rdquo; Si insists. &ldquo;Consistent, co-located teams.&rdquo; Teams should be able to be disbanded and created at-will or &ldquo;just in time&rdquo; as the need arises. Teams are created to attack &ldquo;focal points,&rdquo; or areas that need attention right away. This is an especially hard pill to swallow, since many of us like the familial feeling that comes with long-term teams. Not to mention the nightmares of billing if you&rsquo;re a consulting company.</p>

<h3>Conclusion</h3>

<p>There were a few other speakers at the conference, but none hit quite as close to home as the three I&rsquo;ve discussed. Overall a very interesting conference and a very fun experience. I&rsquo;m excited to think about these ideas and I&rsquo;d like to attempt to use some of them to make my teams more efficient and maybe even a little happier. It looks like the general flow is to move away from massive amounts of process, working more like Lean Startup or Anti-fragile teams.</p>

<p>A decade from now, we&rsquo;ll be living in a post-anti-fragile world wondering what on earth we were thinking in this world of rules, definitions, estimations, and process.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Let me be a billboard for DuckDuckGo for a few minutes]]></title>
    <link href="http://larry-price.com/blog/2014/02/22/let-me-be-a-billboard-for-duckduckgo-for-a-few-minutes/"/>
    <updated>2014-02-22T17:47:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://larry-price.com/blog/2014/02/22/let-me-be-a-billboard-for-duckduckgo-for-a-few-minutes</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I would describe my job as 10% cleverness, 10% tenacity, 30% historical knowledge, and 50% searching the internet.</p>

<p>As you can see, a good search engine is extremely important to me. My job depends on it. Opening <a href="//www.chromium.org/Home">Chromium&rsquo;s</a> history, I can see that I have recently searched for microwaves, <a href="//rubygems.org/gems/activesupport">activesupport</a> compatibility in <a href="//www.ruby-lang.org/en/">ruby 2.1.0</a>, deleting branches in git, and glibc backwards compatibility.</p>

<p>I don&rsquo;t use <a href="//google.com">Lord Google</a> as my default search engine. Instead I use <a href="//duckduckgo.com">DuckDuckGo</a>. From <a href="//en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Duck_Duck_Go">Wikipedia</a>:</p>

<blockquote><p>DuckDuckGo is an Internet search engine that emphasizes protecting searchers&#8217; privacy and avoiding the &ldquo;filter bubble&rdquo; of personalized search results. DuckDuckGo distinguishes itself from other search engines by not profiling its users and by deliberately showing all users the same search results for a given search term. DuckDuckGo also emphasizes getting information from the best sources rather than the most sources&hellip;.</p></blockquote>

<p>The gist is that DuckDuckGo does not personalize your search results based on demographics or search history. It doesn&rsquo;t store your IP address and it doesn&rsquo;t log your information. You cannot &ldquo;log in&rdquo; to the DuckDuckGo website.</p>

<p>Getting down to brass tacks: How does it do search?</p>

<p>Searching on DuckDuckGo for queries such as &ldquo;Will Ferrell&rdquo; or &ldquo;Markdown&rdquo; will give you a blurb at the top of your search results from Wikipedia about that matching query. Searching programming topics (like &ldquo;ruby random array&rdquo; or &ldquo;asp.net create table&rdquo;) will give you a near-matching StackOverflow answer. Searching for a single word will usually give you the definition.</p>

<p>A query that seems mistyped will ask you if you want to correct it. Search speed is comparable to Google, I&rsquo;ve noticed no difference.</p>

<p>Looking at the result of your query, you get your search results middle-aligned. <strong>Middle. Aligned</strong> I know you probably don&rsquo;t think that&rsquo;s a big deal, but go do a Google search right now. It&rsquo;s left-aligned. Same with <a href="//bing.com">Bing</a>. Do you see what&rsquo;s on the right half of your monitor? <strong>Nothing.</strong> When running a Google search with my 22&#8221; monitor (~19&#8221; of horizontal space), there are 13&#8221; of wasted space. About 9&#8221; on Bing.</p>

<p>So, you&rsquo;ve just done a search on DuckDuckGo. Now you can use the Up/Down arrows on your keyboard to navigate the search results. Pressing Enter takes you to the website. I vaguely remember that Google used to allow this, but it seems to have disappeared from the default search results.</p>

<p>Don&rsquo;t like being able to see the combined search results of 50+ search engines? !Bang syntax is the answer.</p>

<p>What is !bang syntax? Let&rsquo;s say you&rsquo;re me and you&rsquo;re looking for over-the range microwaves. I type into my DuckDuckGo search <code>microwaves !a</code> and DuckDuckGo takes me straight to <a href="//amazon.com">Amazon</a>, showing me search results for all those sweet, sweet microwaves. <code>!g</code> takes you to Google, <code>!w</code> takes you to Wikipedia, <code>!gi</code> takes you to Google Images, <code>!yt</code> takes you to Youtube, <code>!lowes</code> takes you to the Lowe&rsquo;s search results, <code>!gog</code> takes you to Good Ol&#8217; Games, and <a href="//duckduckgo.com/bang.html">on and on and on and on and on</a>.</p>

<p>There are <a href="//duckduckgo.com/goodies">100s of other goodies</a> as well. Do math using an &ldquo;=&rdquo; sign, like &ldquo;=128*256&rdquo;. Find &ldquo;Hello, World&rdquo; examples by searching for &ldquo;hello world perl&rdquo; or &ldquo;hello world clojure&rdquo;. Do a Twitter hashtag search to find out what &ldquo;#yolo&rdquo; means. Currency conversions. Unit conversions. Convert between timezones.</p>

<p>Okay, enough shameless plugging for my favorite search engine. Give it a chance. Let those Google servers cool down for a few microseconds, they won&rsquo;t mind.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Tell Your Users When You Fail]]></title>
    <link href="http://larry-price.com/blog/2013/12/12/tell-your-users-when-you-fail/"/>
    <updated>2013-12-12T19:41:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://larry-price.com/blog/2013/12/12/tell-your-users-when-you-fail</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Your users put a lot of faith in you. They put up with your terrible design, your horrible taste in color scheme, and your ability to take up over 100% of their computer&rsquo;s memory. With that in mind, don&rsquo;t these poor people deserve a little bit of honesty?</p>

<p>I came across some code recently that irked me. This code asks for a handle to a database abstraction class and then runs a query on it. It looks kinda like this:</p>

<pre><code class="ruby settings.rb">def changeSettings(newSettings)
  db = dbFactory.get("settings.db")
  if !db.nil?
    db.execute(buildSaveQuery(newSettings))
  end
end
</code></pre>

<p>How nice that <code>changeSettings</code> doesn&rsquo;t try to play with a <code>nil</code> database, right? But what about the user&rsquo;s data? It wasn&rsquo;t saved. And no one knows. <em>Not even you</em>. Now, maybe the user will happily continue what he&rsquo;s doing until he notices that his new settings aren&rsquo;t quite right. So he goes back to them again. Same result. Repeat ad infinitum.</p>

<p>How I would initially approach this is to add an <code>else</code> statement that launches a dialog giving some useful data to the user. Whatever you do, for the love of code, DO NOT tell the user that you had database problems. For most applications, the user will have no idea what that means. It might look something like this:</p>

<pre><code class="ruby settings.rb">def changeSettings(newSettings)
  db = dbFactory.get("settings.db")
  if !db.nil?
    db.execute(buildSaveQuery(newSettings))
  else
    showDialog(title="Save Failed!",
               msg="I'm sorry, but your data could not be saved." +
                   "Press 'Try Again' to give it another go." +
                   "If the problem persists, restart the application" +
                   " or contact system support.")
  end
end
</code></pre>

<p>This is not a bad solution. But what about all the other places in the code I get the database from the factory? I&rsquo;d have to update those as well. It would be better to be able to code the factory to launch a similar error dialog whenever this happens. Even better, let me hand the factory a reference to an appropriate dialog whenever I call <code>dbFactory.get</code>.</p>

<p>Another much more frightening possibility is to skip the <code>nil</code> check. Can you guarantee that <code>dbFactory.get</code> will never be <code>nil</code>? In that case, this option is actually pretty good.</p>

<p>Even if that&rsquo;s not a guarantee you can make, it may still be a valid solution. <a href="http://www.artima.com/intv/defenseP.html">Crash early before you do too much damage</a>. Now, if there&rsquo;s some kind of crash-handler or global exception-catcher in your application, then you can catch the impending crash and tell the user the application needs to be restarted&hellip; And the app probably needs to be restarted anyway! There&rsquo;s no need to keep running after you&rsquo;ve reached some horrible error state that needs to be addressed.</p>

<p>Just do <em>something</em>! Your users (especially if that happens to include me) will appreciate your honesty, even if it&rsquo;s so brutal that they have to restart the application.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
