<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: golang | Larry Price]]></title>
  <link href="http://larryprice.github.io/blog/categories/golang/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://larryprice.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2013-12-15T19:51:19-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://larryprice.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Larry Price]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Setting up a Go environment in Ubuntu]]></title>
    <link href="http://larryprice.github.io/blog/2013/12/15/setting-up-a-go-environment-in-ubuntu-12-dot-04/"/>
    <updated>2013-12-15T18:40:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://larryprice.github.io/blog/2013/12/15/setting-up-a-go-environment-in-ubuntu-12-dot-04</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Some very light cajoling led me to do some investigation into <a href="http://golang.org/">Google Go</a> (often called <strong>golang</strong> for ease of internet search). This is a brief recounting of how I got up and running on <a href="http://ubuntu.com">Ubuntu</a> (first 12.04 and then 13.10). Luckily, this has been made espcially easy for us with the introduction of a <a href="http://packages.ubuntu.com/precise/golang">golang package in the Ubuntu package repositories</a>. There are also <a href="http://golang.org/doc/install">official installation instructions</a> if you don&rsquo;t like mine.</p>

<p>Open up a terminal and let loose:</p>

<p><code>bash
$ sudo apt-get install golang
</code></p>

<p>The download is pretty heavy, so this step may take some time. Eventually the installer for <code>golang-go</code> will ask you if you want to &ldquo;Report installation of public packages to Go Dashboard.&rdquo; I&rsquo;ve been choosing &ldquo;No&rdquo; to this question and have no complaints.</p>

<p>Now comes the fun part. Serious Go development relies on having a &ldquo;workspace&rdquo; setup involving a specific directory structure including <code>bin/</code>, <code>pkg/</code>, and <code>src/</code> directories. Google&rsquo;s <a href="http://golang.org/doc/code.html">official set-up page</a> contains more information about these workspaces.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;m not a big fan of putting a visible directory in <code>$HOME</code>, so I opted to make a hidden directory called <code>.go</code>. After creating the directory, the environment variable <code>$GOPATH</code> needs to be set and <code>$PATH</code> needs to be adjusted.</p>

<p><code>bash
$ mkdir ~/.go
$ echo "GOPATH=$HOME/.go" &gt;&gt; ~/.bashrc
$ echo "export GOPATH" &gt;&gt; ~/.bashrc
$ echo "PATH=\$PATH:\$GOPATH/bin # Add GOPATH/bin to PATH for scripting" &gt;&gt; ~/.bashrc
$ source ~/.bashrc
</code></p>

<p>Now I&rsquo;m going to create a go project and add a link to it in the workspace I just created.</p>

<p><code>bash
$ mkdir -p $GOPATH/src/github.com/user
$ mkdir ~/hello-go
$ ln -s ~/hello-go ~/.go/src/github.com/user/hello-go
</code></p>

<p>For some actual test code, I&rsquo;ll add a file in my <code>hello-go/</code> directory called <code>hello.go</code> with the following code:</p>

<p>``` go hello.go
package main</p>

<p>import &ldquo;fmt&rdquo;</p>

<p>func main() {
  fmt.Println(&ldquo;Hello world&rdquo;)
}
```</p>

<p>Now I&rsquo;m going to install the binary created from compiling this code into my <code>$GOPATH</code> to verify that my workspace is set up correctly, then I&rsquo;ll run it to behold the fruit of my efforts.</p>

<p><code>bash
$ go install github.com/user/hello-go
$ hello-go
Hello world
</code></p>

<p>Installing is not necessary every time I want to test that my code compiles; running <code>go build</code> in the source directory will create a local executable that can be executed for incremental testing.</p>

<p>If you&rsquo;re interested in learning golang, I would recommend doing the <a href="http://tour.golang.org/">go tour</a>. It goes way beyond a trivial hello world program and gives you some insight into many coplex go concepts (I even posted <a href="https://gist.github.com/larryprice/7647808">my solutions as a gist</a>, if you&rsquo;re interested).</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
