<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: sendgrid | Larry Price]]></title>
  <link href="https://larry-price.com/blog/categories/sendgrid/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="https://larry-price.com/"/>
  <updated>2017-08-31T19:53:36-05:00</updated>
  <id>https://larry-price.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Larry Price]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[larry@larry-price.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Sending emails with Pony and Sendgrid]]></title>
    <link href="https://larry-price.com/blog/2014/07/08/sending-emails-with-pony-and-sendgrid/"/>
    <updated>2014-07-08T05:53:26-04:00</updated>
    <id>https://larry-price.com/blog/2014/07/08/sending-emails-with-pony-and-sendgrid</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It&rsquo;s incredible how easy it is to send emails through a web application, there&rsquo;s no wonder we get so much spam. Assuming we have a <a href="http://ruby-lang.org">ruby</a> app using <a href="http://sinatrarb.com">Sinatra</a>, <a href="http://adam.herokuapp.com/past/2008/11/2/pony_the_express_way_to_send_email_from_ruby/">Pony</a> is one of the easiest ways to get started with your own spam empire.</p>

<p>Installation is, as always, trivial with ruby. Install the gem with <code>gem install pony</code> or add <code>gem pony</code> to your <code>Gemfile</code> and run <code>bundle install</code>.</p>

<p>I like to configure Pony in my application&rsquo;s <code>configure</code> block. I could also add it to my <code>config.ru</code>, but I like to keep that file as tiny as posible to avoid having configuration code all over the place.</p>

<pre><code class="ruby web.rb"># ...

require 'pony'
require 'sinatra/base'

class Application &lt; Sinatra::Base
  configure do
    # ...

    Pony.options = {
      :via =&gt; :smtp,
      :via_options =&gt; {
        :address =&gt; 'smtp.sendgrid.net',
        :port =&gt; '587',
        :domain =&gt; 'myapp.com',
        :user_name =&gt; ENV['SENDGRID_USERNAME'],
        :password =&gt; ENV['SENDGRID_PASSWORD'],
        :authentication =&gt; :plain,
        :enable_starttls_auto =&gt; true
      }
    }
  end

  # ...
end
</code></pre>

<p>This block tells Pony to use the <a href="http://sendgrid.com/">SendGrid</a> server to send mail, use the &ldquo;myapp.com&rdquo; HELO domain, and dig up the username and password fields from my environment.</p>

<p>If you&rsquo;re using <a href="https://heroku.com">Heroku</a> to host your application, you can <a href="https://addons.heroku.com/sendgrid">sign up for a SendGrid account through your Heroku app</a>, which gives you instant access to your SendGrid account. The <code>username</code> and <code>password</code> field you need to fill in your environment are automatically populated in your Heroku config, which you can view by running <code>heroku config</code> for your application. The free account gets you up to 200 emails a day.</p>

<p>Since I might have multiple developers working in my source code and testing the email-sending functionality, I have all the developers <a href="https://sendgrid.com/user/signup">sign up for their own free SendGrid account</a>. This should help to alleviate some of the email volume from any particular account while developing. After signing up, it took my account nearly 4 hours to be &ldquo;provisioned&rdquo; (see: approved) by the SendGrid team. Once you&rsquo;re approved you can start sending emails using your developer account credentials. I stick my username/password in my local <code>.env</code> file (another reason to make sure you&rsquo;re not storing your environment on your server or in your git repo).</p>

<p>So let&rsquo;s actually send an email. Let&rsquo;s create a route that sends an email to verify a new user account; I&rsquo;ll take some liberties by saying we have a <code>User</code> model defined already that generates a signup verification hash. I can tell pony to send a plaintext body through the <code>body</code> option and an HTML body through the <code>html_body</code> option.</p>

<pre><code class="ruby web.rb"># ...
post '/signup' do
  user = User.create! params

  url = "#{request.base_url}/account/reset/#{user.generate_verification_hash}"
  Pony.mail(
    to: user.email,
    from: "MyApp Help Desk &lt;noreply@myapp.com&gt;",
    subject: "MyApp Account Verification",
    body: "A request has been made to verify your MyApp account (https://myapp.com)." +
          "If you made this request, go to " + url + ". If you did not make this request, ignore this email.",
    html_body: haml(
      :verify_account_email,
      layout: false,
      locals: {
        email: user.email,
        date: DateTime.now.strftime("%H:%M:%S%P %B %d, %Y"),
        ip: request.ip,
        url: url
      }
    )
  )
end
</code></pre>

<pre><code class="haml views/verify_account_email.rb">%p
  Hello!
%p
  An account verification has been requested for your new &lt;a href="https://myapp.com"&gt;MyApp&lt;/a&gt; account.

%ul
  %li
    Username: #{locals[:email]}
  %li
    Time: #{locals[:date]}
  %li
    IP address: #{locals[:ip]}

%p
  If you made this request, click the link below or copy-paste the following URL into your browser to verify your account:

%p
  %a{href: "#{locals[:url]}", alt: "Verify", title: "Click to verify account"}
    #{locals[:url]}

%p
  If you did not request this new account, please ignore this email.

%p
  Sincerely,
  %br
  Team MyApp

%p
  This email account is not monitored and will not receive replies. For more information, contact &lt;a href="mailto:connect@myapp.com"&gt;connect@myapp.com&lt;/a&gt;.
</code></pre>

<p>When you have a user hit this route, an email will be sent to the user with the given subject, to, from, and body fields using the configuration parameters given in the previous <code>configure</code> block. Fast, easy, and, best of all, no <code>sendmail</code> configuration.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
