<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: ads | Larry Price]]></title>
  <link href="https://larry-price.com/blog/categories/ads/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="https://larry-price.com/"/>
  <updated>2018-04-25T20:56:55-05:00</updated>
  <id>https://larry-price.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Larry Price]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[larry@larry-price.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Go for Web Development 50% Off Sale]]></title>
    <link href="https://larry-price.com/blog/2016/01/21/go-for-web-development-50-percent-off-sale/"/>
    <updated>2016-01-21T10:51:22-05:00</updated>
    <id>https://larry-price.com/blog/2016/01/21/go-for-web-development-50-percent-off-sale</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>At the end of 2015, I published a video course on getting started with web development in Go. For the next two weeks, you can get it for 50% off using this link: <a href="http://bit.ly/1PEubnd">http://bit.ly/1PEubnd</a>. With over 2 hours of content for just over $20, it&rsquo;s a great deal. The sale runs from 21 Jan until 4 Feb 2016.</p>

<p><a href="http://bit.ly/1PEubnd"><img src="https://i.imgur.com/tTPQj2b.png" /></a></p>

<p>The video takes the student through every step of creating a personal library web application from scratch, covering concepts such as routing, database access, and authentication. It&rsquo;s a great introduction to go, and an excellent primer to starting your own go-based web project.</p>

<p>All this comes with the added benefit of supporting me: your local developer. :)</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Go for Web Development]]></title>
    <link href="https://larry-price.com/blog/2015/12/30/go-for-web-development/"/>
    <updated>2015-12-30T14:54:11-05:00</updated>
    <id>https://larry-price.com/blog/2015/12/30/go-for-web-development</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I have published a video series on building web applications in Go called <em><a href="https://www.packtpub.com/web-development/go-web-development-video">Go for Web Development</a></em>.</p>

<p>These videos will guide you through the entire process of creating a web application in Go, all the way from spinning up a basic web server to multi-user authentication. In the end, you&rsquo;ll learn how to vendor dependencies and deploy the application to heroku. Throughout the course, you&rsquo;ll learn to utilize many of the most popular go packages including gorilla/mux, negroni, gorp, ace, and bcrypt. You&rsquo;ll learn about making asynchronous requests from the browser back to the web server, and you&rsquo;ll learn to access external REST APIs from your web server. You&rsquo;ll use go&rsquo;s struct tags to parse both XML and JSON, and you&rsquo;ll use struct tags to access database entities with gorp.</p>

<p>I spent many late nights creating this course, and I&rsquo;ve learned a lot of lessons about creating screencasts along the way. I was also able to solidify much of my base understanding of the go language and learn about many features I don&rsquo;t often utilize. The videos are published by Packt Publishing, and they were a great help along the way. The most valuable lesson I learned from doing these screencasts is that a quality microphone makes a huge difference, and I would have saved myself a lot of trouble had I used my Rock Band microphone from the beginning. In the end everything turned out great. I&rsquo;m relieved to be finished and excited to have an official ISBN connected to my name.</p>

<p><s>The video is currently only $5 for the holidays, but</s> the regular retail price is set to $75 (which is still a bargain considering all the content).</p>

<p>Link: <a href="https://www.packtpub.com/web-development/go-web-development-video">https://www.packtpub.com/web-development/go-web-development-video</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
