<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: mongo | Larry Price]]></title>
  <link href="https://larry-price.com/blog/categories/mongo/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="https://larry-price.com/"/>
  <updated>2019-02-09T13:14:01-06:00</updated>
  <id>https://larry-price.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Larry Price]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[larry@larry-price.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The wisdom of Confucius - now available in an API]]></title>
    <link href="https://larry-price.com/blog/2014/10/14/the-wisdom-of-confucius-now-available-in-an-api/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-14T06:03:16-04:00</updated>
    <id>https://larry-price.com/blog/2014/10/14/the-wisdom-of-confucius-now-available-in-an-api</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I make a lot of silly things while learning new technology. In this case I have tapped into the almighty power of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Confucius">Confucius</a>, a Chinese philosopher from 2500 years ago credited for writing or editing many Chinese classic texts. Growing up as an American child, I associated Confucius with proverbs, and I associated proverbs with that classic after-Chinese-dinner dessert <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fortune_cookie">the fortune cookie</a>.</p>

<p>Fortune cookies are a pure delight: a message in a bottle from the restaurant&rsquo;s proprietors for you to enjoy as you kindly vacate the facility.</p>

<p>Most fortune cookies that I&rsquo;ve opened recently have three parts: a fortune (generally a proverb), a lesson in simplified Chinese, and a lottery number. So many secrets wrapped up in such a small, golden treasure.</p>

<p>Ever left a Chinese restaurant, gotten in your car, and felt the need to break something only to realize you left your precious fortune cookie on the table? I have built a solution.</p>

<p><a href="http://fortunecookieapi.com/">The Fortune Cookie API</a> is a simple, RESTful API built to generate fortune cookie data. The root URL shows documentation built using <a href="https://apiary.io/">Apiary.io</a>.</p>

<p>How does it work? I need fortunes now!</p>

<p>There are options. You can get <code>fortunes</code> from the <a href="http://fortunecookieapi.com/v1/fortunes">/v1/fortunes</a> endpoint, <code>lessons</code> from the <a href="http://fortunecookieapi.com/v1/lessons">/v1/lessons</a> endpoint, and lottery numbers from the <a href="http://fortunecookieapi.com/v1/lottos">/v1/lottos</a> endpoint. By default you get 100 of any model, but all endpoints include a <code>limit</code> (max 1000), <code>skip</code>, and <code>page</code> parameter to facilitate getting all the lessons and fortunes. For lottery numbers, we approximately build <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Powerball">Powerball</a> numbers except we currently ignore the rule for red balls, which means there are something ike 42 billion different possibilities. Due to the high number of potential lottery numbers, the <code>lottos</code> endpoint also includes a <code>firstId</code> parameter that lets you start from anywhere.</p>

<p>But there&rsquo;s no need to get the individual models (unless you&rsquo;re into that kind of thing)! I also created a <a href="http://fortunecookieapi.com/v1/cookie">/v1/cookie</a> endpoint to retrieve a random fortune, lesson, and lottery number as a single object. Woohoo! You can specify the number of cookies (max 100) with the <code>limit</code> parameter.</p>

<pre><code>GET http://fortunecookieapi.com/v1/cookie

{
  "fortune": {
    "id": "53ffcf1d4ea4f76d1b8f223e",
    "message": "This fortune intentionally left blank"
  },
  "lotto": {
    "id": "001000200030004000500006",
    "numbers": [10,20,30,40,50,6]
  },
  "lesson": {
    "id": "53ffcf1d4ea4f76d1b8f2241",
    "chinese": "因特网",
    "pronunciation": "yintewang",
    "english": "internet"
  }
}
</code></pre>

<p>Now you can fill that hole in your heart where the fortune cookies are missing. If you&rsquo;re interested in the code, you can <a href="https://github.com/larryprice/fortune-cookie-api">check it out on Github</a>.</p>

<p>UPDATE: I&rsquo;ve registered the domain <a href="http://fortunecookieapi.com">fortunecookieapi.com</a> for the love of fortune cookies. Enjoy.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
