<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: reactjs | Larry Price]]></title>
  <link href="https://larry-price.com/blog/categories/reactjs/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="https://larry-price.com/"/>
  <updated>2017-08-26T18:50:11-05:00</updated>
  <id>https://larry-price.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Larry Price]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[larry@larry-price.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How To ReactJS]]></title>
    <link href="https://larry-price.com/blog/2015/06/16/how-i-reactjs/"/>
    <updated>2015-06-16T20:03:36-04:00</updated>
    <id>https://larry-price.com/blog/2015/06/16/how-i-reactjs</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://facebook.github.io/react/">ReactJS</a> is a component-based Javascript library for creating user interfaces. I used it extensively on recent side project <a href="https://www.refer-madness.com">Refer Madness</a> (<a href="https://github.com/larryprice/refermadness">source code</a>). It&rsquo;s pretty neat. Let&rsquo;s build some demos!</p>

<p>We&rsquo;ll start small. We can start with the ReactJS sample and figure out what&rsquo;s going on:</p>

<p><iframe style="width: 100%; height: 150px" frameborder="0" seamless="seamless" src="//jsfiddle.net/qqaerhp6/embedded/result,html,js/light/"></iframe></p>

<p>We create a React component <code>Hello</code> and we tell it what to render. When we create a <code>Hello</code> component, we take in an attribute called <code>name</code> which we then access in our component with <code>this.props.name</code>. When the page loads, React will render the <code>Hello</code> component in the element with ID &ldquo;container&rdquo;.</p>

<p>Components can have other components.</p>

<p><iframe style="width: 100%; height: 250px" frameborder="0" seamless="seamless" src="//jsfiddle.net/qqaerhp6/4/embedded/result,html,js/light/"></iframe></p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve created a <code>Name</code> component to show the name. This component uses its children to display any content it needs to. Obviously, this is a bit contrived.</p>

<p>Things get more exciting when we add events. Let&rsquo;s add an event to our <code>Name</code> component: when a user clicks this component, we&rsquo;ll reverse the name.</p>

<p><iframe style="width: 100%; height: 250px" frameborder="0" seamless="seamless" src="//jsfiddle.net/qqaerhp6/5/embedded/result,html,js/light/"></iframe></p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve introduced state to the component. When I want a React component to use state, I need to implement the <code>getInitialState</code> method to tell React what the state is when the component is created. In this case, I set the <code>name</code> field of the component&rsquo;s state to <code>this.props.children</code>. When I render the component, I use the <code>name</code> variable I set in my state object. I add an <code>onClick</code> event and call a method on the component called <code>clickme</code>. In <code>clickme</code> I call the built-in <code>setState</code> method and update the <code>name</code> variable on my state object. Any other state variables on the component would remain unchanged. Any time <code>setState</code> is called, <code>render</code> is called again for this component and any children which need to be updated will also rerender.</p>

<p>Sometimes something happens on a child component that the parent cares about. This time, I want the parent component to know when the <code>Name</code> component gets a click event.</p>

<p><iframe style="width: 100%; height: 250px" frameborder="0" seamless="seamless" src="//jsfiddle.net/qqaerhp6/6/embedded/result,html,js/light/"></iframe></p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve told my child component to call the method <code>goodbye</code> on the parent element using the property name <code>onClicked</code>. When the method is called Ichange the state of the <code>Hello</code> component and update the greeting; in this case, the <code>Name</code> component will be reused since it hasn&rsquo;t changed.</p>

<p>Just a reminder that you can have multiple of any component; just be sure to not duplicate IDs!</p>

<p><iframe style="width: 100%; height: 250px" frameborder="0" seamless="seamless" src="//jsfiddle.net/qqaerhp6/7/embedded/result,html,js/light/"></iframe></p>

<p>I dynamically create as many <code>Name</code> components as I need. I take my list of names and map them all to React components, each of which has a different value. As above, all of these can have events or can call events on the parent component. When we create a list of components, React prefers it when we give them all <code>key</code> attributes. This allows React to cache the components and recreate the appropriate component when states change.</p>

<p>Of course this is just scratching the surface. I used ReactJS because it was fast, stable, and easy to get started learning. It gave me a different way to think about the relationship between my Javascript and the DOM. For a little bit more React you should check out <a href="http://facebook.github.io/react/docs/tutorial.html">the tutorials</a>. If you hadn&rsquo;t noticed, React uses a twist on the Javascript syntax called JSX. If you&rsquo;re into that kind of thing, I&rsquo;ve written about <a href="/blog/2015/06/08/compile-jsx-with-docker/">using Docker to compile your JSX</a> whenever you update your JSX files - very handy IMO.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
