<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: mvc | Larry Price]]></title>
  <link href="http://larry-price.com/blog/categories/mvc/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://larry-price.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-08-02T20:32:12-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://larry-price.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Larry Price]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[On the Futility of Man and Trying to Divide a Sinatra App into Separate Controllers]]></title>
    <link href="http://larry-price.com/blog/2013/08/26/on-the-futility-of-man-and-trying-to-divide-a-sinatra-app-into-separate-controllers/"/>
    <updated>2013-08-26T22:35:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://larry-price.com/blog/2013/08/26/on-the-futility-of-man-and-trying-to-divide-a-sinatra-app-into-separate-controllers</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Oh, <a href="http://www.sinatrarb.com/">Sinatra</a>. You&rsquo;re oh-so-very dear to me. You made it so easy for me to write my <a href="http://capitalpunishment.herokuapp.com">first</a> <a href="http://pokephile.herokuapp.com">web</a> apps. All I had to do was write a couple routes and throw together a few HTML-like files and I had a web app. I used pattern matching to reduce the web-facing code for <a href="https://github.com/larryprice/CapitalPunishment">Capital Punishment</a> from ~500 lines of code to &lt;100 lines of code. You are perfect for writing small-time web applications.</p>

<p>But what about large web applications? What about a web app that has normal users and admin users, makes lots of database reads and writes (my previous apps only did reads from a user-facing perspective), and has to be able to show the history of everything, forever, to the authorized users who request it?</p>

<p>You see, Sinatra is kind of an <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Model%E2%80%93view%E2%80%93controller">MVC framework</a>, but not exactly. In Sinatra, you have Views (your HTML inter-mixed with Ruby code in your desired DSL) and you have Controllers (each of your routes). When a database is involved, you can use something like <a href="https://github.com/bmizerany/sinatra-activerecord">ActiveRecord</a> or <a href="http://mongoid.org/en/mongoid/index.html">Mongoid</a> or <a href="http://datamapper.org/">DataMapper</a> and you have yourself Models.</p>

<p>So every route is kind of a Controller. Every. Route. In Capital Punishment, there were once 8 routes (there are now 7). In the project I&rsquo;ve been working on recently, there are currently 56 routes. 56 routes in the language described above means I kind of have 56 controllers.</p>

<p>That&rsquo;s been pretty overwhelming, especially since the traditional way of creating routes in Sinatra is to shove them all in the same file. There are a few ways I could think of to address this. The way we chose six months ago (for better or worse) was found <a href="http://stackoverflow.com/questions/5877000/what-is-a-controller-in-sinatra">on StackOverflow</a>, and involves creating a bunch of different files where you shove all related routes. So you get this situation:</p>

<p>``` ruby app.rb
class App &lt; Sinatra::Base
end</p>

<p>require_relative &lsquo;controllers/helpers&rsquo;</p>

<p>Dir.glob(&ldquo;#{File.dirname(<strong>FILE</strong>)}/controllers/*.rb&rdquo;).each do |file|
  require file.chomp(File.extname(file))
end</p>

<p>class App
  get &lsquo;/&rsquo; do</p>

<pre><code>erb :home
</code></pre>

<p>  end
end
```</p>

<p>``` ruby controllers/reports_controller.rb
class App
  get &lsquo;/reports/user_bills&rsquo; do</p>

<pre><code>erb :user_bills_report
</code></pre>

<p>  end
  &hellip;
end
```</p>

<p>And so on and so forth. This works fine for a while, but we&rsquo;ve ended up with 13 &ldquo;controller&rdquo; files, many of which are not trivial. This also makes the App class quite large since its controllers handle most of the logic for the app. This also doesn&rsquo;t enforce any kind of URL-naming logic, so if a developer is working hard (s)he may create both <code>/reports/user_bills</code> and <code>user_info_reports</code> without realizing the inconsistency (s)he just injected into the system.</p>

<p>In hindsight, this method is not perfect. I think that the Rails method of individual controllers is significantly better for large apps. Some people have been using other methods for trying to make Sinatra more MVC, such as <a href="https://github.com/jorrizza/sinatra-mvc">sinatra-mvc</a>. To be frank, sinatra-mvc pretty much does the same thing we&rsquo;ve done, but with more structure.</p>

<p>I think what I&rsquo;ve learned is that you should use a tool for its intended purpose. Sinatra was written to quickly create web apps in Ruby with minimal effort. Once you have more than 10-15 routes, you should reconsider whether your app can still be called &ldquo;minimal effort.&rdquo; Sinatra may fly you to the moon, but you&rsquo;re unlikely to see what spring is like on Jupiter or Mars.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
